Good morning, today's דף *daf* is ד *dalet* but we start on
the very top of ג עמוד ב *gimmel amud bet*. So there's
a lot of גמרא Gemara *Gemara* again because there's not only the
רש״י *Rashi* although I should say that רש״י *Rashi* does not become
as verbose as we continue, but there's no תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* and
you really see how that makes a difference because there's a lot
of גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in every דף *daf*. So we're going to
try to really focus for today and get a little past caught
up. I want to say one thing about yesterday which is that
I think I misstated the position that we said before about כרת
karet. בחוטא *karet b'choteh* to tell you כרת kares, *karet* and not
מלכות Malkus *malkus*. The point there was not that you get מלכות
*malkus* and כרת kares *karet*, which is what I might have said,
so I'm sorry about that. The point there according to that opinion,
which we don't פוסקן *pasken* by, is that you for the things
that you get כרת kares, *karet* you do not get מלכות *malkus*.
There's no concept of מלכות *malkus* based on בית דין *Beis Din*
administer מלכות *malkus*, the punishment is כרת kares, *karet*. That was that
position. We don't פוסקן *pasken* that way, we פוסקן *pasken* you get
מלכות *malkus*, you can get מלכות *malkus* and if you do you're
exempt from כרת kares *karet*. Anyway, picking up with what we were
talking about, we were dealing with the idea of how many חטאות
chatas *chata'ot* you can bring and the idea that by things like
שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* and עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* you can
bring one if you make a mistake about the fundamental issue. You
can bring individual ones if you make a mistake about the individual,
so if you forget the מלאכות melachos *melachos*, ten מלאכות *melachos* you
and you do all ten you bring ten חטאות chatas *chata'ot*. If
you forget שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* then you would only bring one. And
by עבודה זרה avoda zara, *avodah zarah* if you forget the prohibition
of particular עבודות avodas, *avodos* you bring for bowing down, for slaughtering,
all the different עבודות avodas *avodos*, whereas if you forget fundamental עבודה
זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* and you do multiple things you only
bring one. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said how could you forget fundamental
עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah zarah* and you're still doing an act
of עבודה זרה avoda zarah, *avodah zarah*? And it said אומר מותר
*omer mutar*, you think that it's allowed. Okay, and there and that
makes you a שוגג *shogeg* even if you were completely oblivious of
the entire category, not just of a detail, but of the entire
category. So that raises interesting questions of how we categorize אומר מותר
*omer mutar*. But then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so now you
forgot the entire category, you forgot the category and the details. So
do we treat that as multiple or do we treat that as
one? And that's a question, but generally we so that's a debate,
but that's a question, but generally we treat that as only one
fundamental mistake and one חטאת chatas. *chatas*. Now we continue four lines
from the top of ג עמוד ב *gimmel amud bet* within this
vein. רב פפא אמר amar *Rav Pappa amar*, רב פפא *Rav Pappa*
said, משכחת לה בתינוק שנשבה לבין העובדי כוכבים *mishkachat lah b'tinok shenishba
l'vein ha'akum*. It's
similar to an example of אומר מותר *omer mutar* is somebody that
was an infant that was taken captive amongst the amongst the non-Jews,
somebody who grew up thinking he was not Jewish. And that's a
place where you can fundamentally not know the prohibition. But of course
that's basically a version of אומר מותר *omer mutar* and then the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on to describe it in a more it's
more of אונס *ones*, it's true I should actually say there's a
debate in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* whether that's
אונס *ones* or שוגג *shogeg*. The conclusion is שוגג *shogeg* in the
sense that you have to bring a קרבן korban חטאת chatas, *korban
chatas*. Now that is bizarre, you see because שוגג *shogeg* normally implies
some sense of fault. And what type of fault does somebody who
grows up thinking that they're not Jewish because they were taken as
an infant? So what it really does point to, I should say,
is the idea that חטאת chatas, *chatas* is not just for guilt,
a חטאת chatas, *chatas* is for the objective fact that a sin
was done. And therefore if you're an אונס *ones* in the sense
that somebody forced you, held a gun to your head, it was
a force of nature, something like that, then you could say it's
not even my action. But to the degree that you're choosing and
doing it even if you're blameless, there actually is a sense that
that sin requires atonement and you have to bring a חטאת chatas
*chatas*. So that actually is an interesting discussion regarding תינוק שנשבה *tinok
shenishba*, which is a discussion in שבת shabbos *Shabbat*, but it's an
excellent question, but we actually rule that not שוגג *shogeg* in terms
of blame but enough as enough that you are the doer that
you have to actually bring a חטאת chatas *chatas*. Okay, so that
was enough to end it there, it would just be like an
extreme version of אומר מותר *omer mutar*. But then the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* goes on to qualify it and really make it a different
case. So let's take a look. דידע דאסירא עבודה זרה avoda zarah.
*d'yada d'asira avodah zarah*, that you know that עבודה זרה avoda zarah
*avodah zarah* is אסור asur *assur*. I don't know how you knew
that, maybe you knew it was אסור assur *assur* because of שבע
מצוות בני נח *sheva mitzvos bnei Noach*, that'd be an interesting question.
If you knew it was אסור *assur* as שבע מצוות בני נח
*sheva mitzvos bnei Noach*, how does that factor in if you happen
to be a Jew? Anyway, והאיי עבודה זרה avoda zarah לא ידע
דאסירא *v'hai avodah zarah lo yada d'asira*, but you don't know this
particular עבודה זרה avoda zarah. *avodah zarah* that you're doing is אסור
*assur*. So somehow again it's hard to imagine the case. You grew
up knowing you're not supposed to worship עבודה זרה avoda zarahs, *avodah
zarah* X but not עבודה זרה avoda zarah *avodah zarah* Y and
therefore you worshipped עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *avodah zarah* Y, so that
was a case of you fundamentally thought that worshipping the בעל Baal
*Baal* was מותר *mutar*, you only thought worshipping the אשרה Asherah, *Asherah*
was forbidden and therefore that is one fundamental mistake even though you
did all the various עבודות avodas *avodos*. Again, you could have understood
that better if the guy grew up knowing he was Jewish. How
exactly that mixes with the scenario of growing up thinking you're not
Jewish is not exactly clear. What? All right, let's not go there
right now. Let's say you grew up in the in the בעל
*Baal* cult. So you thought that that's that's what I want, that
would be interesting, right? If you thought that from your religion, from
the בעל *Baal* cult, בעל *Baal* was permissible and אשרה Asherah. *Asherah*
was forbidden and then you went so you knew the idea of
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, *avodah zarah* but from within your religion, not
from within a Jewish perspective. I don't know if that's what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, but that would be fascinating if we
were to use those issues to define שוגג *shogeg*, מזיד *meizid*, אונס
*ones* and so on.
Unfortunately Jewish history is
full.
That's an interesting thought. Okay, yeah, you have like some family tradition
not really knowing what it's about. Yeah, I always grew up knowing
you weren't supposed to do this and maybe you grew up because,
right, you have a vague awareness where this is from. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara's goes on. ואיבעית אימא ve-iba'it eima and if you
want you could say,
אפילו תימא בגדול afilu teima begadol כגון דקטעי בהדין קרא, kegon de-katai
ve-haden kra, even if it's an adult, meaning not somebody that was
an infant in captive, so we're back to a normal ישראל, Yisrael,
and here though is the mistake. לא תעשון אתי אלהי כסף ואלהי
זהב לא תעשו לכם. lo ta'asuni iti elohei chesef ve-elohei zahav lo
ta'asu lachem. Don't make gods of gold and silver. סבר, savar, כי
כתיב השתחויה לעבודה זרה דכתיב זהב, ki ketiv hishtachavaya le-avoda zara de-ketiv
zahav, when is it forbidden? To gods of gold and silver. אבל
מידי אחריני, aval mi-dei achrinei, if you make an idol out of
other forms, שריא, sharya, it's permissible. So it's similar like the בעל
versus the אשרה, it's a peer case explaining how if you grew
up knowing you're Jewish you could make such a mistake because you
look too much at the פסוק. pasuk. So therefore you think that
worshipping something of wood is permissible. It's a fundamental mistake, even if
you did all the עבודות, avodas you would only bring one
חטאת. chatas? דהיינו שגגת כרכבן, de-hainu shegagat karkavan, that's making a fundamental
mistake about the prohibition. וזדון עבודה, vezadon avoda, but you knew, but
you did עבודות avodos. that you knew were wrong, because you knew
these עבודות would be wrong if they were done to gods of
gold or silver, or in the previous case that it was done
to the אשרה. So you knew the עבודות were an issue, you
just thought that this type of עבודה avoda to this god was
permissible. Okay, אמר תנא, amar tanna, okay, אמר whatever. דאסיף ליד, de-asif
le-yad, okay, ורב פפא בריה דרב איקא משמיה דרב ביבי אמר, ve-Rav
Papa brei de-Rav Ika mishmei de-Rav Bibi amar, תנא שם שבת ושם
עבודת כוכבים קתני. tanna shem Shabbat ve-shem avodat kochavim katani.
Don't get hung up that why did it say one if you
really could get thirty-nine, why did it say one by עבודה זרה
avodah zarah if you could get four, and we think we're trying
to list them as the maximum number of חטאות chatos you can
bring. No, we're not trying to list the maximum, we're just listing
the categories. So we're saying there's שבת shabbos category of a חטאת,
Chatat there's עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, we're not trying to list how
many חטאות chatos are possible in each category. Like you just said
about עריות. arayot.
Yeah, maybe, but I guess there's a difference in the sense that
by שבת shabbos and עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah? the חידוש chiddush is
at the end of the day you're transgressing one לאו. lav. Not
to do מלאכה melacha or not to be עובד עבודה זרה, oved
avoda zara, and the חידוש chiddush is that those, is that if
you do it in separate ways you actually bring a separate חטאת,
Chatat right? Whereas by the עריות arayot they're completely, although they are,
can be defiled, but they are separate prohibitions. So,
and here it's basically saying so these are the prohibitions, שבת shabbos
and עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah, But thank you, that's a good clarification.
Okay, Rashi with לא תבערו אש.
lo teva'aru esh.
Yeah, but no, whatever that's coming to do with, still not, you're
not going to get מיתה misa for לא תבערו אש lo teva'aru
esh or חטאת, Chatat, however you understand what that פסוק pasuk is
about. Let's go on. Okay, ושם ממי, ve-shem mi-mai, how do I
know that? מדקתני, mi-de-katani, הבא על אשה ובתה ועל אשת איש, ha-ba
al isha u-vitah ve-al eshet ish, a man who has sex with
a woman and her daughter or a married woman. ויש בתו מאנוסתו
דלא קתני לה. ve-yesh bito me-anusato de-lo katani la. Now that doesn't
list every single חטאת Chatat, by עריות. arayot. Why? There's the idea
of a daughter that is not your wife's daughter. A daughter of
a woman born out of wedlock, a daughter born out of wedlock.
Now for some strange reason the גמרא Gemara doesn't call it בתו
ממפותתו, bito mi-mefutato, right, his daughter from a woman he seduced, it
calls it בתו מאנוסתו, bito me-anusato, a woman he raped, which I
don't know why it describes such a drastic case. But the point
is his daughter, his biological daughter that is not his wife's daughter.
Okay, so that's a prohibition, but that's not listed. Why? It's a
חיוב כרת, chiyuv karet, yeah, but it's not explicit in the תורה
Torah and it's not listed even though it's a separate prohibition and
a separate כרת. kares, Okay, so
דלא קתני לה, de-lo katani la, it's not in the משנה. Mishnah.
How is it a separate prohibition?
What? How is it a separate?
Well, where do we learn it from? We learn it from because
it says בת בתו. bat bito. It says,
now you have to, I'm trying to find the פסוק, pasuk,
how do you know that when your daughter is forbidden it's your
daughter through your wife?
Oh, no, there's one פסוק pasuk is אשה ובתה. isha u-vitah. And
we understand that אשה ובתה isha u-vitah doesn't mean a woman and
her daughter but basically your wife and her daughter.
Okay, so that's the prohibition we're talking about? No. So that would
not be a biological daughter that is not your wife's daughter. Your
biological daughter that is not your wife's daughter is a separate פסוק
pasuk which it says
something about sleeping at בת בתו ואת בת בנו לא תשכב, bat
bito ve-at bat bino lo tishkav,
I can't remember the exact פסוק pasuk off the top of my
head. But it speaks about granddaughter, it doesn't speak explicitly about daughter,
but it doesn't mention the mother, it just mentions the daughter there.
Okay.
The reason why it may be rape is because then you might
not have knowledge that this is your daughter, but you're still חייב.
chayav.
Could be, okay, maybe. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so how about that? Why didn't it mention that?
So the גמרא Gemara says, דכתיבן קתני דלא כתיבן לא
קתני. de-ketivan katani, de-lo ketivan lo katani.
No, we're only doing things that are מפורש meforash in the פסוקים.
pesukim. Okay, maybe daughter isn't מפורש meforash in the פסוק, pasuk, ואיכא,
ve-ika, now there's a question of the text, but basically the text
is בת בתו. bat bito. בת בתו ובת בנו bat bito u-bat
bino דכתיבא ולא תני. de-chtiva velo tani.
It's ironic, right? But granddaughter is mentioned in the פסוק pasuk but
not daughter. So at least say granddaughter; that is מפורש mefurash in
the פסוק. pasuk. אלא שם אשה ובתה
קתני. ella shem isha u-bita katani.
So you know why we didn't? Because we distilled it all into
one category of אשה ובתה. isha u-bita. Even though there's a halachically
a difference between your wife's daughter and your biological daughter, essentially it's
a concept of daughter, and therefore we consolidated it. So sort of
like דוסא בן הרכינס Dosai ben Harkinas consolidated all the עריות, arayos,
but here at least things that are essentially the same we consolidated,
even though there are extra חטאות chatos, that we could have listed.
So we're not trying to maximize the number of חטאות chatos, there
would be.
So minimize the 39 or whatever it was, not 39,
34, 36. Yeah, so that's it.
The גמרא Gemara yesterday said the number was to tell you number
of חטאות, chatos. but first of all we're noting it's not 36,
34, 33. So anyway, once the number is not telling you an
exact number of חטאות, chatos, what's the point anyway? So that's what
this גמרא Gemara is moving towards. Don't get so hung up. We're
not maximizing חטאות. chatos. הכא נמי שם שבת ושם עבודה זרה קתני.
hacha nami shem shabbos veshem avoda zarah katani.
Here too, so we could have given more, but we're trying, you
know, we're consolidating certain things. We're not trying to maximize the number.
רב אחא בריה דרב איקא רמי דיליה אדיליה. Rav Acha brei de-Rav
Ika rami dilei adilei.
So רב אחא בריה דרב איקא Rav Acha brei de-Rav Ika showed
a contradiction between these two statements of רב ביבי בר אביי. Rav
Bibi bar Abaye. מי אמר רב ביבי בר אביי התם שם שבת
קתני ושם עבודה זרה
קתני? mi amar Rav Bibi bar Abaye hasam shem shabbos katani veshem
avoda zarah katani? Didn't he say this, that in the end our
משנה mishna is talking about like, you know, consolidating categories and it's
not trying to maximize the numbers? ואיתמר, ve-itmar, we have another ברייתא,
braisa, המעלה אברי פנים בחוץ חייב אברי חוץ בחוץ חייב. ha-ma'aleh evarei
pnim bachutz chayav evarei chutz bachutz chayav. That what
the prohibition of שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, bringing a קרבן korban outside
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So if you shechted it, obviously you're
doing it all outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But let's say
you're only offering up, you're burning the limbs on the altar outside
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. This is to God, not to עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah. but it's still חייב כרת. chayav kares. So anyway,
there's two scenarios. One is of a קרבן korban. that was shechted
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you took the limbs out and
you offered them outside. The other is something you did the entire
thing outside. And here we have a ברייתא braisa that says either
way, whether it's אברי פנים בחוץ, evarei pnim bachutz, stuff that was
inside that brought outside, or stuff that started outside that was
outside, either way you're חייב. chayav. וקשיא ליה לרב ביבי בר אביי.
ve-kashya lei le-Rav Bibi bar Abaye. רב ביבי בר אביי Rav Bibi
bar Abaye was, you know, had a problem. אי הכי, ei hachi,
if that's true that those are separate חיובים, chiyuvim, he understood that
to be separate, meaning you would bring a separate חטאת Chatat if
you did both of those. הא תנן שלשה ושש כריתות בתורה? ha
tnan shlosha ve-shesh krisos ba-Torah? Why does it say 36? Plus and
37 they are. דאיכא המעלה והמעלה. de-ika ha-ma'aleh ve-ha-ma'aleh.
There are two forms of bringing, and he understood them to be
distinct, not just saying the category includes both, but those are distinct.
So it should have listed two different forms of burning limbs to
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah מאי קשיא ליה? mai kashya lei? What's bothering
him? So what's bothering him? He just said by a שבת shabbos
and עבודה זרה Avoda Zara, we're consolidating. So here too, ניתני שם
העלאה קתני. nisni shem ha'ala katani. So let's just say there's one
prohibition of bringing limbs, I mean it's true you could have separate
חטאות, chatos. but category it's one thing. מי דמי? mi dami? No,
they're not similar. We would, although we would group one, we wouldn't
group the other. Why? מי דמי? mi dami? שבת ועבודת כוכבים תני
יתנהון אבינכיהון. shabbos ve-avoda kochavim tani yasun abincheihon. A strange word, but
it means in their place. So שבת Shabbos and עבודה זרה avoda
zara where there are מסכתות masechtos that deal with שבת Shabbos and
there is also a גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, there's an elaboration
of עבודה avoda, זרה. So there when we'll, we have a place
to discuss all the different מלאכות of שבת Shabbos. and that you
can bring 39 חטאות. chatos, And we have a place to discuss
all the different עבודה זרה, ways of doing עבודה, and that you
can bring separate חטאות. chata'os. So there they're explained somewhere else. When
we get to this משנה, mishna, we'll consolidate. There's no need to
spell it all out. So wait until we get to... There you
go, right. גבי כריתות דאיירי משני שם שבת ושם עבודת כוכבים תני.
gabei krisos de-irya meshani shem shabbos veshem avoda kochavim tani. So by
כריתות krisos where we're talking about it now, there we'll say we'll
consolidate because you know what, we'll get to it, we'll talk about
those details, here we can consolidate. That's an answer. But גבי העלאה
מי תני יתנהון אביניהון דשני הכי? gabei ha'ala mi tani yasun abineihon
de-shani hachi? But by offering things outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
there's no other place we're going to talk about it. You know
where we're going to talk about it? Here, in our מסכתא. masechta.
So if those were separate categories, you should have told it to
me here in כריתות, krisos, because here is where is the place
to discuss it. Okay, so that is the answer and basically the
point is yes, our משנה mishna is not maximizing the חטאות, chata'os.
it is giving you, it is consolidating certain things that warrant consolidation.
The interesting thing to note though is that the משנה mishna I
believe does not say the different forms of being שחוטי חוץ, shchutei
chutz, right? It doesn't say shechting and העלאה, ha'ala, does it mention
those separately? I don't think... Oh yes, it does. השוחט והמעלה. ha-shocheit
ve-ha-ma'aleh. So it does have both of those. Yes, so question, Mordechai,
does this indicate that this is a rather late text that assumes
a knowledge of every discussion in all the other rest of the...
No, גמרא's... Gemara first of all, even at the mishnaic level, שבת
Shabbos, and עבודה זרה are spelled out. שבת Shabbos, in שבת and
עבודה זרה in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So it doesn't even have to refer
to other גמרות. Gemaras. There are some גמרות Gemaras that very do
say כדבעינן למימר לקמן, Ki-d'va'inan l'meimar l'kamman, and those are core, you
know, or and those clearly are are very late. But this could
just be basically because it's at the משנה Mishnayic level. Listen, so
in this one we do have two separate ones because we should
have, was Rebbe's question, we should have had it separate because there's
no other place to discuss it. So if they were really
separate categories, it should have been discussed here. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on. בעי מיניה רמי בר חמא מרב חסדא. Ba'ei
minei Rami bar Chama me-Rav Chisda. Two כריתות krisos and one לאו,
lav, מהו? mahu? Now before we discussed two לאוין lavin and one
כרת, kares. which was מעלה ma'aleh and which was מפטם וסך mefatem
ve-sach of the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. And we said the fact
that they're separate לאוין lavin even though it says only כרת kares
once makes them separate and you would bring separate חטאות. chata'os. Again,
all of these mean in one state of forgetfulness. If you remember
in the middle or whatever, you know, then obviously even if it's
the same sin, separate חטאות. But our discussion is one state of
forgetfulness. So before we said that if it's two separate לאוין lavin
and one כרת, Karet, מפטם וסך, mefatem ve-sach, separate חטאות. What if
it's the flip? Two כריתות krisos and one לאו. lav. The Torah
says a separate כרת, Karet. but it only prohibits them with one
prohibition. Now, let's find it, it's an interesting question, let's first see
if such an example exists. מהו, Mahu, what would be that case?
אמר ליה, Amlei, שוחט והעלאה קאמרת. shocheit ve-ha'ala amart. So, so that,
so what is that? That must be the case of שחיטה shechitah
and bringing things outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Because what does
the פסוק pasuk say? There, there are what? It says one prohibition,
let's see, רש"י Rashi quotes it. It says כריתות krisos twice and
one לאו. lav. The לאו lav is השמר לך פן תעלה עלתיך
בכל מקום אשר תראה. hishamer lecha pen ta'aleh olotecha be-chol hamakom asher
tir'eh. Don't bring your קרבנות korbanos outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
The כרת Karet is separate. It says there, it says whatever, anyway
רש"י Rashi quotes it. Okay, you'll take my word for it. So
anyway, the גמרא Gemara word for it. Anyway, there's just one prohibition,
but it says explicitly if you do this you get כרת, Karet
if you do that you get כרת. Karet? Is the fact that
it says a separate כרת Karet enough for a different חטאת? Chatat.
So the גמרא Gemara says, הני שני לאוין נינהו. hani shenei lavin
ninhu. But that's not, their question is moot because that really is
two separate לאוין. lavin. Why? The Torah only says once, don't bring
קרבנות. korbanos. How is it two separate לאוין? lavin? איכא דאמר מגזירה
שוה. ika man de-amar mi-gezeirah shavah. There's an opinion about how we
learn out a separate לאו. lav. There's an opinion that says we
learn it out from a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. נאמר כאן הבאה
ונאמר להלן הבאה. ne'emar kan hava ve-ne'emar le-hallan hava. It says here
הבאה, hava, it says ופתח אהל מועד לא הביאו, u-le-pesach ohel mo'ed
lo hevi'o, that if you brought it, if you brought it outside
and you didn't bring it to the tent. So that's, you know,
you brought it outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And it also
says elsewhere הבאה. hava. What does it say elsewhere הבאה? hava? It
says, I'm sorry, just checking רש"י Rashi here. ופתח אהל מועד לא
הביאו, u-le-pesach ohel mo'ed lo hevi'o, that's by שחיטה. shechitah. And by
העלאה ha'ala it says ופתח אהל מועד לא יביאנו. u-le-pesach ohel mo'ed
lo yevi'ennu. Okay, so by both of those it says you did
not bring them to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So we'll say,
ah, so it says, uses the same phrase. מה להלן לא ענש
אלא אם כן הזהיר אף כאן לא ענש אלא אם כן הזהיר.
ma le-hallan onash ela im kein hizhir af kan onash ela im
kein hizhir. So it's true we have one prohibition, but notice the
prohibition emphasizes העלאה. ha'ala. The prohibition says פן תעלה עלתיך. pen ta'aleh
olotecha. So we'll say, okay, there's a prohibition of העלאה. ha'ala. It's
not generic, it's on העלאה. ha'ala. But since העלאה ha'ala and שחיטה
shechitah outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash are compared, same phrase לא
הביאו, lo hevi'o, if there's a prohibition by העלאה, ha'ala, there's a
prohibition by שחיטה. shechitah. So there's a separate prohibition. Now you have
to understand what the גמרא Gemara is doing here is important. The
גמרא Gemara has a general principle which is אין עונשין אלא אם
כן מזהירין. ein onshin ela im kein mazhirin. The Torah will not
give you a punishment unless there was a negative prohibition. Now once
you have that position, what do you do by the fact if
you find the Torah gives punishment and it didn't spell out the
prohibition? So we have to find a way to discover prohibition. And
sometimes the way we discover prohibition is not by saying oh this
פסוק pasuk is אסור it. We sort of discover it because it's
inferred. We discover it based on the י"ג מדות.
yud gimmel middos. So but we so now created a prohibition or
discovered a prohibition by שחיטה shechitah because of a גזירה שוה. gezeirah
shavah. Since there's a prohibition by העלאה ha'ala and there's a גזירה
שוה, gezeirah shavah, it's telling you there's also a prohibition by שחיטה.
shechitah. So the אין עונשין מן הדין ומזהירין מן הדין ein onshin
min ha-din u-mazhirin min ha-din so to speak. Well no, not מן
הדין, min ha-din, it's not קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. Okay, אין מזהירין
מן הדין ein mazhirin min ha-din also, but this is גזירה שוה.
gezeirah shavah. It doesn't mean you don't use the י"ג מדות, yud
gimmel middos, it just means you don't use קל וחומר. kal va-chomer.
We talked about that yesterday as well. Okay, so therefore, so it
is a separate prohibition from גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. ואיכא דמייתי לה
מהיקש. ve-ika de-maiti lah me-hekkesh. And some learn it out not from
a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah but a היקש, hekkesh, more like a
comparison than a linking of words. אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse
says שם תעלה ושם תעשה. sham ta'aleh ve-sham ta'aseh. There only in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash should you offer up and there should
you do, meaning the other things like שחיטה. shechitah. מקיש שחיטה להעלאה.
makish shechitah le-ha'ala. So it's comparing the offering up to the other
parts of bringing the קרבן. korban, מה העלאה לא ענש אלא אם
כן הזהיר, mah ha'ala lo onash ela im kein hizhir, so the
same way by העלאה ha'ala it's clear that there's a prohibition, פן
תעלה, pen ta'aleh, אף שחיטה לא ענש אלא אם כן הזהיר. af
shechitah lo onash ela im kein hizhir. So even by שחיטה shechitah
it is the same. So it's an interesting question, what would happen
if we would have one prohibition and two כריתות, krisos, but so
far we haven't found that. Because if you were thinking about שחיטה
shechitah and העלאה, ha'ala, both actually are, we learn out a distinct
prohibition. Can I ask a question from my own... that's מחלוקת... machlokes...
So then he is מן הדין *min hadin* even if... No, מן
הדין *min hadin* specifically means קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. Does so okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: דילמא בי שתי
מיתות Mitot, בלאו אחד אמר רחמנא *dilma bei shtei mitos belav echad
amar rachmana*. So he does I can't find your exact case of
two כרתס *kareis*s with one לאו Lav *lav*. What I can find
is two מיתות Mitot, *mitos* with one לאו Lav. *lav*. Where do
you have that? מאי *Mai*, אוב Ov וידעוני *ov veyidoni*. By אוב
ov, וידעוני *ov veyidoni*, two forms of necromancy, it says לא ימצא
בך *lo yimatze becha*, well not לא ימצא בך *lo yimatze becha*,
what's the פסוק Pasuk? *pasuk*? לא ימצא בך *lo yimatze becha* etc.
etc. ושואל אוב ov. וידעוני *veshoel ov veyidoni*. It is the לא
ימצא בך *lo yimatze becha*. So do not have somebody who is
a שואל אוב ov וידעוני *shoel ov veyidoni*. It's all the same
prohibition. But then it says separately that if somebody who does who
does it, it says what does it say? אוב ov או ידעוני
Yidoni מות יומת *ov o yidoni mos yumas*. Now you would say
that's also one מיתה Mitah *mita*, but because it says A or
B מות יומת *mos yumas*, it considers that to be a distinct
מיתה Mitah, *mita*. So even there you would have you know you
would have questioned that, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying okay
we're willing to consider that as a separate מיתה Mitah, *mita* because
it says A or B, but the it's one prohibition. It says
לא ימצא בך שואל אוב וידעוני *lo yimatze becha shoel ov veyidoni*,
so that's considered basically one prohibition. So maybe that's the case you're
talking about. Not a כרת karet. *kares*, but a מיתה Mitah, *mita*,
one prohibition, two מיתות Mitot, *mitas*. Would you bring a separate חטאת
Chatat, *chatas* if you did both? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אמר ליה Amar lei, *amar lei*, ולאו אחד אמרת *ve'lav echad amart*.
מאי אוב וידעוני *Mai ov veyidoni*? אמר ליה *Amar lei* דהא פלוגתא
דרבי יוחנן וריש לקיש *deha plugta deRabbi Yochanan veResh Lakish*. That is
a debate which you just if that's your question then that's a
debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish *Rabbi Yochanan
veResh Lakish*. דתנו גבי הנסקלין *Detanu gabei haniskalin*, we learned in the
פרק *perek* of הנסקלין *haniskalin*, בעל אוב Baal Ov וידעוני *ba'al ov
veyidoni*, if we have the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* in סנהדרין Sanhedrin, *Sanhedrin*
that two things that you're חייב מיתה Chayav Mitah, *chayav misa* for,
they get סקילה Skilah, *sekila*, is the one who does the אוב
וידעוני *ov veyidoni*. דקשיא לן *Dekashlan*, מאי שנא גבי סקילה Skilah תני
ידעוני Yidoni וגבי כריתות לא תני ידעוני Yidoni, *mai shna gabei sekila
tani yidoni vegabei krisos lo tani yidoni*? Right? So we have a
standing we have a question, right, good question, right? Here in our
משנה Mishnah, *mishna* it says only אוב *ov*, and in סנהדרין Sanhedrin
*Sanhedrin* it says אוב *ov* and ידעוני Yidoni? *yidoni*. Why does it
separate it and not separate it here? So obviously that suggests an
answer, suggests that because it only is one לאו Lav *lav*, you
would only get one כרת karet. *kares*.
So I mean you'd only bring and there'd be one כרת karet.
*kares* and you'd only bring one קרבן korban *korban*. No, same thing
as before, we're doing categories. But why categories there and not there?
And the so alright, but maybe it could have given that answer,
but let's see where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes with this. Okay,
so why in סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* does it separate and not there?
So אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *amar Rabbi Yochanan*, so we know
that there's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan? וריש לקיש *Rabbi
Yochanan veResh Lakish* how to explain that. So אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan, *amar Rabbi Yochanan*, הן ושניהן בלאו אחד נאמרו *hen ushneihen belav
echad ne'emru*. It says like בדיבור אחד נאמרו *bedibur echad ne'emru*. הן
ושניהן בלאו אחד *hen ushneihen belav echad*. No. So he basically says
what you're suggesting, that since it's one לאו Lav, *lav*, even though
it's separate מיתות Mitot *mitos*,
you're only going to bring one חטאת Chatat, *chatas*. So on the
one hand, two לאוין
*lavin* and then one כרת karet *kares*, separate לאוין *lavin* שמות *shemos*
different שמות *shemos*, that is separate חטאות *chataos*. One שם *shem* and
two times it says מיתה Mitah *mita*, but it's the same category,
the same לאו Lav *lav*, only one חטאת Chatat, *chatas*. That's what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says. הן ושניהן בלאו אחד נאמרו
*hen ushneihen belav echad ne'emru*. ונימא ידעוני Yidoni ולא נימא בעל אוב
ba'al ov *Venema yidoni velo nema ba'al ov*. Okay, so fine. Now
we get why he said only one and not two. Why did
you pick אוב *ov* rather than ידעוני Yidoni *yidoni*? אמר ליה *Amar
lei* wait why would you say this one in the משנה Mishnah,
*mishna*? Because our משנה Mishnah *mishna* is talking about כרת karet *kares*
for the purpose of חטאת Chatat. *chatas*. So the if so there
it's talking about separate things you could do to get מיתה misah?
*mita*, each one is separate, and it says a separate מיתה *mita*.
But if it's a question of how many חטאות *chataos* you could
bring, right, here's the answer to your question. So basically it's saying
this is one category then, right? No, it's not simplifying and consolidating.
It's actually telling you a הלכה *halacha*, that even if you did
both of them, you would only bring one חטאת Chatat. *chatas* because
it's the same לאו Lav *lav*. So that's exactly the question which
was raised, right? The overarching question here is, are these distinct categories,
distinct for a חטאת Chatat. *chatas*, if you did it all in
one state of forgetfulness? So we said on the one hand, מפטם
וסך שמן המשחה *mefatem vesach shemen hamishcha*, although it says כרת karet.
*kares* once, separate לאוין *lavin* would be a separate חטאת Chatat, *chatas*.
Here it's the flip, one prohibition, two separate מיתות misas. *mitas*, if
you did both of them you're only going to bring one חטאת
Chatat *chatas*. So it is actually it's a halachic point. I understand.
So if you warn me for an אוב *ov* and then I
go to ידעוני yidoni *yidoni* then that would have been good enough,
meaning I'm still considered to have been warned? No, that's a that's
a סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* question. That's not a this question. This is
a חטאת Chatat, *chatas* question. Okay, there actually we do treat them
separately. Alright, here's the חטאת Chatat *chatas* question. Okay, so גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ונימא ידעוני yidoni? ולא נימא בעל אוב ba'al ov, *venema
yidoni velo nema ba'al ov*. So if you're going to pick one
in our משנה Mishnah *mishna* to tell you only get one חטאת
Chatat *chatas* even if you do both of them, what did why
did you pick אוב *ov*, why not pick ידעוני yidoni, *yidoni*? Alright,
קסבר Kasavar, הואיל ופתח הכתוב בבעל אוב *kasavar hoil upatach hakatuv beba'al
ov*. There you go. Alright, פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* started with it, we
had to pick one. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, אמר *Resh Lakish amar*,
now okay, so that's basically your question is answered. Because there's only
one לאו Lav *lav*, separate מיתות *mitas* is not enough to say
separate חטאות *chataos*. Now we're dealing with a different question. Why did
our משנה Mishnah, *mishna* mention אוב *ov*? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* said a simple thing, it's the first in the פסוק
pasuk? *pasuk*. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, אמר *Resh Lakish amar*, ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Resh Lakish* had a more interesting halachic answer. הואיל ואין
בו מעשה ma'aseh, *hoil ve'ein bo ma'aseh*. You don't do an מעשה
ma'aseh *ma'aseh*. Why don't you do an מעשה *ma'aseh* by ידעוני Yidoni,
*yidoni*? You don't do an מעשה *ma'aseh* by ידעוני yidoni *yidoni* because
apparently it's like you put some I don't know bone in your
mouth or whatever and it sounds like some some some some thing
is speaking through you and that's not considered an מעשה *ma'aseh*. Because
you're not doing anything physical. How about the fact that you're well
yeah but the putting in your mouth is... not the prohibition. It's
whatever you're doing to get the spirit. So what will be by
אוב and ידעוני yidoni again? Oh אוב is you're doing some physical
act let's say waving your hands or whatever right. So anyway you
don't really do an act and therefore, therefore what? Therefore remember we
said this yesterday, חטאת Chatat, you learn out from the paradigm of
עבודה זרה, and the only time you bring a חטאת Chatat. is
by something that is about an act. So for ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish you really don't know the answer to the question of what
if it was one לאו Lav. and two separate מיתות, because for
him there's a different reason you don't bring a חטאת, Chatat and
a different reason why it's not in the משנה. Mishnah The reason
you don't bring חטאת, Chatat the reason you don't bring משנה, Mishnah
not because it's one category, but because there's no act that's been
done. And the גמרא Gemara says, but what about? That's the debate,
we're going to get there. That's going to where we're getting there,
okay? So that's what he says. So according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan you have your answer, only one חטאת Chatat, because it's one
לאו. Lav According to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish. presumably not. That's not
enough, he says, because it's not an act and that's why it's
not in the משנה, Mishnah that's why there's no חטאת. Chatat. הא
גופא קשיא, Ha Gufa Kashya, for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish מאי טעמא
לא אמר כרבי יוחנן? Mai Ta'ama Lo Amar KeRabbi Yochanan? Why didn't
he say like רבי יוחנן? אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar, רב פפא, did
you say? No, you get כרת, karet you just you need an
act for חטאת, chatas and our purpose of our משנה Mishnah is
to get you to a חטאת, chatas. okay? So the issue of
an act is for חטאת, chatas not for כרת. karet So אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, and also not only that, you get
סקילה, you get so you don't need an act to get סקילה
for certain things, like מגדף Megadef and whatever, there are things that
everybody agrees are חייב מיתה, chayav misah but there's still you still
every but you still need an act in order to bring a
חטאת. chatas I see, so you can get מיתה and you can
get כרת karet. but there's no חטאת. chatas, Exactly. Exactly. It's a
little bit ironic, but yes. Everybody agrees מגדף Megadef gets מיתה, there's
a debate if מגדף Megadef gets a חטאת. chatas. Everybody agrees בעל
אוב ויידעוני Baal Ov VeYidoni get מיתה, there's a debate if ידעוני
yidoni gets a brings a חטאת, Chatat, is that considered an act
or not an act? Okay, so that's good to clarify. It's ironic
of course that you can get the worst punishment without doing an
act. You don't get מלקות Malkut without doing an act, but you
can get כרת and מיתה, that's also quite ספק, Safek, there are
always exceptions to the rules, but you cannot get a חטאת Chatat
without an act. Yeah, it's just an interesting moot point, in other
words, you get killed but you don't bring a חטאת, Chatat right?
No, no, no, there are different scenarios. One is you did it
willfully and there were witnesses, and the other is you did it
unintentionally. Right, we're constantly flipping when we're talking about these between the
scenario whether it was willful and witnesses and warning, or whether it
was unintentional. Do you still get the מלקות Malkut for to replace
the כרת? Yes, if there was an act. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says, now no, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, וריש לקיש מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבי יוחנן? VeReish Lakish
Mai Ta'ama Lo Amar KeRabbi Yochanan? Why did ריש לקיש Reish Lakish.
not say like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan say you do get a
חטאת chatas, for it and it was just being and it was
just that there's only one because it's one פסוק? pasuk. So אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, דהא חלוקין הן במיתותיהן, DeHa Chalukin Hen
BeMitoteihen, because he exactly debates that point. He actually says that if
you have one לאו lav, but it says מיתה separately, that's a
separate category. So your question, one לאו, lav, separate מיתות, is a
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish? רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says because of one לאו lav. you'd only bring
one חטאת chatas if you did both, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish,
says that's enough to make them separate categories. Okay, both agree to
two כרתים, Karetin, right? Yes, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, אמר לך, Amar
Lecha, חלוקה דלאו הוי חלוקה, Chalukah DeLav Havei Chalukah, חלוקה דמיתה לא
הוי חלוקה. Chalukah DeMitah Lo Havei Chalukah. No, that's exactly what they
debate. He says if you have a separate לאו lav it's a
separate category for a separate חטאת, chatas, if it's one לאו lav.
and it says two מיתות, that is not a separate category. So
great, so the question you raised was the debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish Now we're going to go,
now that we've said that, we're going to now focus on this
issue about אין בו מעשה, Ein Bo Ma'aseh, about what constitutes an
act in order to bring a חטאת. chatas רבי יוחנן מאי טעמא
לא אמר כריש לקיש? Rabbi Yochanan Mai Ta'ama Lo Amar KeReish Lakish?
Why did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan not say like ריש לקיש? Reish
Lakish קסבר, מאן תנא כריתות, Man Tanna Keritot, רבי עקיבא היא, Rabbi
Akiva Hi, דאמר לא בעינן מעשה. DeAmar Lo Ba'inan Ma'aseh. So he
says no, because רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, as we know, what else
is in our משנה Mishnah that you bring a חטאת chatas. for?
מגדף. Megadef. So at the end of the משנה, Mishnah somebody, you
know, there's the opinion of the חכמים, Chachamim, oh no חטאת chatas
for מגדף, Megadef, no action. But the סתם Stam of the משנה
Mishnah. held even a מגדף Megadef brings a חטאת, chatas, you don't
need an action for a חטאת. Chatas So therefore you can't exclude
ידעוני, yidoni? you're not excluding מגדף, Megadef, how could you how could
you exclude ידעוני? yidoni That seems to be a pretty good argument.
ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish what would ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say back?
So here's where ריש לקיש Resh Lakish distinguishes what constitutes an action.
והא רבי עקיבא לא בעי מעשה רבה, VeHa Rabbi Akiva Lo Ba'ei
Ma'aseh Rabbah, that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva doesn't need a big action,
okay, that's true. If you're a מגדף, Megadef, somebody's a מגדף, Megadef,
he blasphemes God, that's enough of an action. But that's still an
action, it's a verbal action. מעשה זוטא בעי, Ma'aseh Zuta Ba'ei, he
still needs some type of an act. And therefore even רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is only saying that a verbal act is enough. Now
why is a ידעוני yidoni not even that? So let's take a
look. בעל אוב מאי מעשה אית ביה? Baal Ov Mai Ma'aseh It
Bei? What action is there by the בעל אוב ba'al ov case?
הקשת זרועותיו, Hakashat Zero'otav, הוי מעשה. Havei Ma'aseh. So there you're somehow
flapping your arms, you're doing something in this act of conjuring the
spirit, that's an act. Everybody can agree to that. מגדף מאי מעשה
אית ביה? Megadef Mai Ma'aseh It Bei? עקימת שפתיו, Akimat Sfatav, הוי
מעשה. Havei Ma'aseh. So by the מגדף Megadef what action do you
have? You're moving your lips. Verbal act, physical act, that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says. But ידעוני yidoni. even according to the רמב"ם Rambam
who says you're doing this, still though, and we'll talk about this
in a minute, if you can get a sound to come from
you, mmm, mmm, mmm, right, that would not be considered a מעשה,
moving of the lips. So that's what he says, you know what
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, says, cursing is an act, if cursing you
get a חטאת chatat but not because he doesn't need an act,
just because he says that constitutes an act. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva still needs an act, and something like ידעוני yidoni, which has
no act, no moving of the lips, that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would say you do not bring a חטאת. ורמינהו U-reminhu that it
actually works, you know, the really, right, that of course would answer
that. Okay, so anyway, so now you have a fascinating question conceptually,
when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you get it for מגדף, megadef,
is he denying the need of an action or is he saying
it constitutes an act? Now let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara
says כסלקא דעתך, kasalka daitach, oh we just did that. מאי מעשה
דקאמר רבי עקיבא דחשיב מעשה? כסלקא דעתך דחשיב דאטוש ידיה הוי מעשה
זוטא אפילו לרבנן. Mai ma'aseh d'ka'amar Rabbi Akiva d'chashiv ma'aseh? Kasalka daitach
d'chashiv d'atush yadei havei ma'aseh zuta afilu l'rabanan. Now we're assuming that
the flapping of the hands is not considerably different than moving of
the lips. And therefore the rabbis at the end of the משנה
Mishnah that said מגדף megadef doesn't bring the חטאת should also say
you don't bring the חטאת for a בעל אוב ba'al ov because
flapping of hands is not much different than moving of lips. So
now we're going to have a question. So the גמרא Gemara says
מיתיבי, meitivei, אמר רמי בר חמא, amar Rami bar Chama, בעבודה זרה
אינו חייב אלא דבר שיש בו מעשה. b'avodah zarah eino chayav ela
davar sheyesh bo ma'aseh. By עבודה זרה you're only חייב chayav if
you actually do an action. This is in סנהדרין, this is talking
about a חיוב מיתה, chiyuv misah, כגון שזיבח וקיטר וניסך והשתחוה. kegon
shezivach v'kiter v'nisach v'hishtachavah. For example, if you slaughtered or burned incense
or anointed, those are, and or you bowed down, those are the
four primary עבודות. וקשיא לן, V'kashya lan, and we asked, השתחויה לית
בה מעשה, hishtachavayah leis bah ma'aseh, why is bowing down an action?
Now that's fascinating that the גמרא Gemara is asking the question also
by flapping of the arms, you would say of course it's an
action, you know, you're moving your body. But it seems that the
גמרא's Gemara understanding, moving your lips, moving your arms, moving your body,
if it's just movement, it's not an action. It has to do
something. Okay, just physical, that's the question. So that's why we're putting
all these in the same category: moving your lips, flapping your arms,
bowing down, you're not doing anything, you're not physically, you know, doing
something on the real, in the real, you know, sort of interacting
with some thing in the real world, you're just moving your body.
So
the גמרא Gemara says, so why is that an act? ואמר ריש
לקיש, V'amar Resh Lakish, so ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says הא מני
רבי עקיבא היא דאמר לא בעינן מעשה. ha mani Rabbi Akiva hi
d'amar lo ba'inan ma'aseh. It's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that calls all
these things that says that it's an act, that says you don't
need an action,
or what we understand really means you don't need a big action,
all these things count. So if moving your lips counts, bowing your
body counts, and that's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has a lower standard
for action. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, אמר, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said,
אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu teima rabanan, even the rabbis that say that
moving your lips is not an act, כפיפת קומתו הוי מעשה. kfifas
komaso havei ma'aseh.
You bow down
your whole body, that's an action, even though you didn't interact with
anything in the real world, but that degree of a physical action
is a real action, moving lips maybe not.
So here what do we see? We see that according to רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan he says that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva really does
demand an action, but it could be a small action, and his
definition of a small action would include that the רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and the rabbis disagree with would be moving lips, bowing down
the body. So presumably in that category should also be the flapping
of the arms. So why isn't that debated between רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and the חכמים? chachamim? It's just accepting him as a god
and, you know, attesting your fealty to it is nothing. Well, it
might be, but it might also require some action, like you erect
an idol and you say אלי אתה. eli atah. But if I
just go to an idol and say, oh my god, right, so
that has to do with אין בו מעשה, ein bo ma'aseh, yeah,
exactly, those are how that question. So anyway, so let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara says, but there are some times you're
חייב מיתה chayav misah. for אין בו מעשה, ein bo ma'aseh, but
anyway we're not learning סנהדרין right now, what we're extracting from this
is what's relevant to us, which is the question about a מעשה
for a חיוב חטאת. chiyuv chatas. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, so what do we have? So we have that there is
a debate number one whether bowing down is an action that everybody
would agree to, but ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says it isn't, it's
the line between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים. chachamim. So
if bowing down is only רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so flapping your
arms should only be רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So let's take a
look, so the גמרא Gemara says מכלל דסבירא ליה לריש לקיש אליבא
דרבנן כפיפת קומתו לרבנן לא הוי מעשה. m'klal d'savira lei l'Resh Lakish
aliba d'rabanan kfifas komaso l'rabanan lo havei ma'aseh. So according to ריש
לקיש, Resh Lakish bowing down is not an action for the rabbis,
only for רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So that's the dividing line. So
if bowing down is part of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva only, so
הכא דאטוש ידיה הוי מעשה, hacha d'atush yadei havei ma'aseh, how could
you say flapping your arms even the rabbis would agree with that?
Right, if bowing down the rabbis don't agree to, flapping your arms
they also shouldn't. So why do the rabbis not argue on the
case of ידעוני? yidoni? Right, everybody get it? The rabbis in the
משנה Mishnah. argue on the case of מגדף. megadef. Okay, it could
be that the תנא tanna of the משנה Mishnah, says you don't
even need an action, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no you do,
but just a lower definition. Okay, so what's considered to be the
type of action that the rabbis at the end disagree with? So
now that we know that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said the rabbis
at the end say that even bowing down isn't an action, we
know it from another discussion that that's ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish position,
so any like flap, so why do they not also... Why don't
they argue? They only argue on מגדף. Megadef. But if even, but
if the rabbis
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagree even if השתחויה hishtachavaya is considered
an action,
right, that the rabbis would say השתחויה hishtachavaya is not an action,
then they should also say that flapping your arms, ידעוני, Yidoni isn't
an arm, or isn't an action. ידעוני, yidoni oh I'm sorry, you're
right, but oh, thank you, thank you, but okay, thank
you very much,
okay, but the reason ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said ידעוני Yidoni is
not in our משנה Mishnah, is because it's not an act, is
because even according to, thank you very much, okay, I misphrased it,
excellent. So he said the reason ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said ידעוני
Yidoni is not in our משנה Mishnah is because even according to
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it's not an action, right? That's what ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish said, right? He said why is it not? שאין
בו מעשה. She'ein bo ma'aseh. So then you're right, I should have
phrased it differently. So if for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, thank you,
okay, if here's the
point, if for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, same point but I have
to, I should be phrased
this way, if for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva bowing down is an
action and moving your lips is an action, then why is רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva not also saying that flapping your arms is an
action? Yes, thank you,
that is the way to frame it, thank you. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says ואלא כי אמר ריש לקיש הכא בשאר השתחויה דהוי
מעשה זוטא אליבא דרבי עקיבא אבל לרבנן לא הוי מעשה. Ve'ela ki
amar Reish Lakish hacha bish'ar hishtachavaya dehavi ma'aseh zuta aliba deRabbi Akiva
aval lerabbanan lo havi ma'aseh. So now I think I was jumping
ahead to this point in the משנה. Mishnah? So when ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says that flapping your arms isn't an action, what he
means is that it isn't an action for the רבנן. Rabbanan. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would admit that it is an
action. Okay, so that's where I was heading.
Okay, so you're right, first the גמרא Gemara thought that ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish was saying it wasn't even an action for רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. So what's he talking about? Bowing down is an action,
flapping your arms isn't? Okay, fine, for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it
is an action, but for the rabbis it's not an action. So
the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי אמאי תני יצא מגדף שאין בו
מעשה נתני יצא מגדף ובעל אוב. Ee hachi amai tani yatza megadef
she'ein bo ma'aseh nitni yatza megadef uva'al ov. Okay, so I was
jumping ahead. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's true that according
to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it is an action, okay, now we
would have to rely on רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, that really it
doesn't say ידעוני Yidoni but it's really intended to be there, why
did the rabbis not also argue on ידעוני? Yidoni So the גמרא
Gemara says חדא מתרתי קתני. Chada mitartei katani. Fine, it was only
giving one objection. The same way the rabbis objected to מגדף megadef
and said no חטאת, they would object to ידעוני Yidoni as well,
they're not listing all of the things they object to. וליתני בעל
אוב ולא ליתני מגדף. Velitni ba'al ov velo litni megadef. So why
give the example of בעל אוב, ba'al ov why not give the
example of מגדף megadef when they say you need to do an
action and they disagree with, if they're choosing to disagree? So מגדף
איצטריכא ליה. Megadef itztericha leh. No, you have to tell me that
מגדף megadef is, that I would have thought might have constituted an
action more than flapping the arms. Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל וכתיב
כרת דיליה במקום קרבן. Salka da'atach amina ho'il uchtiv kares dileih bimkom
korban. Since it says by מגדף megadef right where it says, you
know, that if you curse God you are ונכרתה, venichratah, it also
is in the context of bringing a קרבן, korban it's juxtaposed to
bringing a קרבן Korban where it appears in the תורה. Torah. אימא
מודי ליה לרבי עקיבא. Eima modi leh leRabbi Akiva. Maybe in that
case even though there's not an action they would admit there's a
חטאת. קא משמע לן דלא. Ka mashma lan dela. So it tells
me that. Okay, so I'm sorry that got a little complicated in
the middle because I jumped ahead, but the basic point is like
this. Conceptually, the rabbis say, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says מגדף megadef
you're חייב. chayav. Is he saying you don't need an action, which
is how רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan interprets it, or is he saying
that constitutes an action, which is how ריש לקיש Reish Lakish interprets
it? If it does constitute an action, what is an action for
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, what is an action for the רבנן? Rabbanan?
And there we said ריש לקיש Reish Lakish added to that even
something which we would have thought, I would have implicitly agreed with
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan השתחויה hishtachavaya is an action, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says no, it's not an action. השתחויה Hishtachavaya is only an
action for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva with a lower definition, not for
the רבנן. Rabbanan. So then we say okay, so for רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, if lips and bowing is an action, then flapping should
also, and in the end you say oh fine, you're right. For
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva actually does agree that ידעוני Yidoni you're חייב,
chayav, it's only the rabbis that disagree, and in the list of
the things the rabbis disagreed, we should have included ידעוני. Yidoni Okay,
so there's a, ידעוני, Yidoni the flapping is the אוב, isn't it?
What? The flapping is the אוב. Are we confusing אוב and ידעוני?
yidoni, The אוב is when you flap, right? ידעוני yidoni is when
the... oh, so it's... alright, I'm trying to go... okay, thank you
Michael. Second time you're correcting me. I'm trying to go way too
fast. Okay, and I'm still not catching up because we're still behind.
Okay, thank you. Okay, okay. You're right. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish,
is, thank you. Alright. So Michael is correct. The ידעוני yidoni is
where the thing is in your mouth, right. So that is still
not in the משנה Mishnah? for the reason ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
originally said. That clearly doesn't have an action, it's nothing, that happens
totally automatically. Thank you very much. The issue here is the בעל
אוב Ba'al Ov, is in the משנה. Mishnah Thank you. The בעל
אוב Ba'al Ov, is in the משנה, Mishnah but that is the
flapping of the arms. Okay, so that's the question. The first question
is, a, so now that the בעל אוב Ba'al Ov is in
the משנה, Mishnah. it's the flapping of the arms, and that's, but
that now that we're saying that that's a debate between רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים, Chachamim, why did the חכמים Chachamim not
disagree also with that? And it's saying you know what, they really
do disagree. Where did that bowing fit in then? Because that was
brought in from another debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan וריש לקיש
about עבודה זרה, whether bowing is considered an action. Where רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said it's not an action and it's only רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said it actually is an
action. Okay, כביכול מה דהוה, Kiviyachol mah dehavah, but the גמרא Gemara
is saying fine. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says
like this. One minute. Let me... okay fine. No, I'm sorry. You
can really tell I'm doing this way too fast. Reverse. Okay. Let's
do this one more time. Try to summarize this one more time.
Okay, basically what you have is the following. Right? First you have
the issue within the חכמים Chachamim that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
that according to the חכמים... Chachamim... one more time. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and the חכמים Chachamim disagree about מגדף. Megadef. According to רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that מגדף... Megadef... that
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does not need any action and the מגדף
Megadef doesn't have an action and the חכמים Chachamim say it does
need an action. According to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says that מגדף Megadef has to do an action, he does
need an action, but even moving of the lips is an action.
So that's number one debate, whether whether רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in
the משנה Mishnah you do need some... you do need an action
but they just have a lower threshold. Based on that, we have
the question about why is ידעוני yidoni. not in the משנה? Mishnah?
Okay, let's do it this way. This will clarify hopefully everything. Let's
do a few things. Why is ידעוני yidoni not in the משנה?
Mishnah ידעוני everybody agrees has no action. You stick the bone in,
you do nothing, everybody agrees ידעוני has no action. רבי יוחנן says,
oh, according to me, I say that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does
not need any action, so I can't say it's not in the
משנה Mishnah, because of no action. I have to say it's not
in the משנה because it was only one לאו. lav Remember getting
back to that question. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, says, no, I say
that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva requires an action, so I know why
ידעוני is not in the משנה. It doesn't have an action. And
actually I would say that if it's two separate מיתות it would
have been a separate חטאת, but it's not in the משנה because
even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva requires an action. So that's one question.
Why is ידעוני not in the משנה? Because of one לאו lav,
or because even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva requires an action? Now we
have another point, which is there's a משנה later that speaks about...
there's an issue about השתחוואה. Hishtachava'ah. And there's a question, why is
השתחוואה Hishtachava'ah listed? It's not an action. So here, רבי יוחנן says,
I actually think השתחוואה Hishtachava'ah is an action. It's a big action.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says it's not an... it's a small action
and it only counts according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So now
what we have clarified is that according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
who says that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva requires a small action, both
moving of the lips and השתחוואה Hishtachava'ah is a small action. ידעוני
is no action. And now, like Michael we were talking about בעל
אוב, Ba'al Ov. fine, we get ידעוני is no action, we get
moving of the lips and bowing down is an action for רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but בעל אוב, Ba'al Ov, which is mentioned in
the משנה, right? בעל אוב Ba'al Ov is the flapping of the
arms, right? That also is an action. So if that's an action
and that's a debate... the things that would be debated between רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים, Chachamim, because if they debate lips
and they debate bowing down, they should debate בעל אוב. Ba'al Ov.
Why don't they debate it? And in the end the answer is
they do debate it. Okay? So for ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva requires an action, small actions include lips, bowing down,
and בעל אוב, Ba'al Ov. and the rabbis really do debate those
cases, they only mentioned one. And now we continue. We have to
continue. So you don't have... you may not have any חטאת even
for the בעל אוב Ba'al Ov, depending on which position you take,
right? If you take the חכמים, Chachamim, then you wouldn't have a
חטאת for בעל אוב. Ba'al Ov Everyone would agree כרת for בעל
אוב. Ba'al Ov Right. Okay. Now, עולא אמר... Ulla amar... okay, man,
we are flying even more on. עולא אמר Ulla amar בעל אוב
דקתני במקטר לשד. Ba'al Ov dekatni bemakter leshed. No, when we say
a בעל אוב, Ba'al Ov the reason the rabbis don't disagree even
if you buy into ריש לקיש and say that the rabbis would
disagree with things like bowing down and lips, they wouldn't disagree with
בעל אוב baal ov because it's not flapping of arms. בעל אוב
baal ov is actually somebody offering up incense to a... to one
of like a spirit. So there's a real action involved. It's not
just arm flapping. So מתקיף לה רבא, Matkif lah Rava, אם כן
היינו עבודת כוכבים. im ken hainu avodat kochavim. Isn't that עבודה זרה?
אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, now you could have said no,
spirits are different than עבודה זרה, you're not worshipping it. Well let's
see what רבא Rava says. מקטר לשד על מנת לחברו. Mekater leshed
al menat lechavro. You're not burning incense to a שד Shed to
worship it, you're doing it as a way to invoke it, to
call it, to control the spirit world. And if you're doing that
and you're not doing it to worship, that's a separate thing. So
why is בעל אוב not debated by the חכמים? Chachamim? Isn't it
considered to be a... so one you might say the חכמים Chachamim
say that is an action, that probably would be what רבי יוחנן
says. ריש לקיש would say, no, that's part of the debate of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים Chachamim and they just don't
spell that out. But here we're saying it's actually an action, it's
a very different type of a thing, it's invoking a שד. Shed.
It's whatever, doing an incense or whatever in order to invoke a
spirit.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye says, אם כן
היינו חובר חבר. im ken hainu chover chaver. One minute, that's חובר
חבר, Chover Chaver, which is another prohibition, which is sort of invoking
the spirits, which he understands...
to be by doing these types of actions like burning incense.
אמר ליה, התורה אמרה חובר חבר כגון זה בסקילה. HaTorah amrah chover
chaver kigovn zeh biskilah.
Now the other part of אביי's Abaye question is that חובר חבר
chover chaver is not a חייב מיתה. chayav misah. חובר חבר chover
chaver is a לאו, lav. which is interesting. So why some things
are a לאו, lav, one things are חייב מיתה. chayav misah. So
says you're right. If you're trying to invoke the spirits, if you
do it in certain ways it's only a לאו. Lav. If you
do it this way, the way of בעל אוב through this through
this burning of incense, then you're חייב מיתה. chayav misah. And what
is חובר חבר? chover chaver? It's also it's also invoking the spirit
but through some not through some different actions. Okay, ואלא חובר חבר
דלאו הידין הוא? ve'ela chover chaver de'lav haden hu? So what is
a חובר חבר chover chaver that would only be a לאו lav
and not מיתה? So אמר ליה כדתניא בחובר חבר אחד חובר גדול
ואחד חובר קטן, amar lei kede'tanya be'chover chaver, echad chover gadol ve'echad
chover katan, whether you are invoking big things or small things and
this could even be animals like you know like in
the idea of witches they have this idea of the familiar.
Anybody hear about that? Like an animal, oh so you don't your
kids don't read this type of stuff. So anyway, there's this idea
like you know you know there's always like an owl with a
witch and a cat or whatever. Anyway, there's an idea that certain
certain like people like of that nature have particular animals that are
their familiar, they're their חבר, chaver, actually חובר חבר chover chaver and
that they are you know and that they do things for them
or whatever you know and they're somehow have some control by the
spirit world or whatever. Anyway, so whether it's a big thing or
a small thing ואפילו חובר לנחשים ועקרבים חייב. va'afillu chover lenachashim ve'akrabim
chayav. Even if you sort of in use your you know you
know these the powers or whatever in order to gather and to
you know and to make a you know and to control snakes
and scorpions. Okay, so that is so if you do it in
some type of invocation or whatever it's a לאו. lav If you
do it through burning the incense to the spirits as the way
of doing it and you're maybe invoking spirits and not just animals,
that's חייב chayav מיתה. אמר אביי האי מאן דבעי למיצמד זיבורא ועקרבא,
Amar Abaye, hai man de'ba'ei lemitzmei diburei ve'akraba, so if you want
to somehow gather up bees or scorpions אסור through some through some
invocations then that's forbidden. That's חובר חבר. chover chaver. ואי קא אתו
בתריה שרי, Ve'ee ka'asu batrei shari, but if they're passing you and
they're going to sting you or bite you then you're allowed. Why?
Is it פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? Maybe it's פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh
and therefore we allow a לאו lav, for פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh?
No, not a חייב chayav well maybe I don't if it's not
עבודה זרה. Anyway, or that he says that it's only if maybe
the purpose you're doing it defines whether it's a prohibition. To do
it for the sake of self-protection is not the context in which
the תורה Torah prohibited it. All right, moving on. לרבי יוחנן דאמר
עקימת שפתיו הוי מעשה, Le'Rabbi Yochanan de'amar akimat sefatav havei maaseh, עקימת
שפתיו נהוי מעשה, akimat sefatav nehavei maaseh, so גבי מגדף. gabei megadef.
Now we're saying like this. Remember ריש לקיש said bowing down is
an act, moving your lips, slapping your arms, all of those are
only according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the the בעל אוב again
not the ידעוני, ידעוני is no action, okay, but all of those
are actions, that's only according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, according to
the רבנן Rabbanan they would disagree with all of those. But רבי
יוחנן says no no no, a bowing down is a real action,
okay, only so now the moving your lips, that's the debate between
the Rabbis and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but bowing down everybody would
agree is a real action. So the גמרא says if that's true,
so עקימת שפתיו נהוי מעשה גבי מגדף. akimat sefatav nehavei maaseh gabei
megadef. The גמרא says we still don't see a difference between lips
and bowing down. You're not interacting with the real world, you're just
moving a body part. So if if רבי יוחנן says that bowing
down everybody agrees is an action, why isn't moving the lips the
same? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, said רבא, Rava, שאני מגדף הואיל
וישנו בלב. shani megadef ho'il ve'yeshno balev. Even though you moved your
lips, it's not fundamentally about the physical action. It's fundamentally about what
you're expressing. Okay, עקימת שפתיו akimat sefatav is defining speech as something
physical. But that's not really what it is. It's really expressing your
thoughts. And if you are רש"י Rashi says in סנהדרין for example
that if somebody happens to say the words of גידוף giduf and
wasn't you know wasn't and wasn't thinking them, wasn't thinking what they
were saying or misunderstanding what they were saying, it would not be
an act of מגדף. megadef. So it's not just saying a formula,
it's actually doing an act of cursing God which depends on what
you're thinking. So although it has an action component, it fundamentally is
an expression of thought and therefore not considered an action the same
way in the same way that bowing down which is fundamentally about
the act is considered an action. Now מגדף megadef yes. Now you
can always say I didn't mean it. How does he well that's
a good well if somebody says don't do this if there's התראה
hasra then התראה hasra probably clarifies it. I thought you were going
to ask the other question which is but then worshipping עבודה זרה
is also also במחשבה bemachshavah because you have to believe that the
thing is a god. But תוספות Tosafot asks that in סנהדרין and
תוספות Tosafot says well I'm maybe paraphrasing תוספות but what I'll say
is is that it's a little different. Yeah I went off track.
It's a little different that there you start by having that belief.
You have to have you have to have a belief. So you
start by believing in this god. But then the focus is now
you did an act of worship. Okay whereas yes it's true if
you didn't believe this is a god it would be meaningless but
in the context of believing this is a god the focus is
the act of worship. The focus is the physical act whereas by
מגדף megadef the focus is on the expression of what you are
thinking. Okay so now the גמרא says אבל בעלמא עקימת שפתיו הוי
מעשה. aval be'alma akimat sefatav havei maaseh. Normally though the גמרא says
you're right if according to רבי יוחנן bowing down is an act.
that moving your lips is an act. So מתיב רבי זירא, mative
Rabbi Zeira, so Rabbi Zeira asks, יצאו עדים זוממים שאין בהם מעשה.
yatzu eidim zomemim she'ein bahem ma'aseh. We have a teaching elsewhere, which
I won't give you the full context, but basically says that עדים
זוממים eidim zomemim is not considered an act. Now normally it's obviously
not to get punished, because you get punished by the עדים זוממים
eidim zomemim כאשר זמם. ka'asher zamam. But for certain הלכות halachos of
bringing a קרבן Korban, or whatever, עדים זוממים eidim zomemim is not
considered an act. Okay, so now we have a question, why is
that not an act? That is a moving of the lips. And
again, if Rabbi Yochanan says bowing is an act, moving of the
lips should be. And the גמרא is consistently not distinguishing between a
big movement of the body like the body and a small movement
like your lips. They also walk forward. ואמאי הוקי. ve'amai hokei. ואמאי
הא על פי כתיב, ve'amai ha'al pi kesiv, that's about what you
say with your mouth. So בהם. bahem. So why is that an
act? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, שאני עדים זוממים הואיל וישנם בראייה. shani
eidim zomemim hovei yeshnam bire'iyah. It's about seeing. Now what does that
mean seeing? Because fundamentally what you're doing is you're testifying to what
you saw. So therefore it's not just about the words you say,
it's about seeing which is not much of an act. But of
course Rava is, these guys are עדים זוממים. eidim zomemim. They didn't
see. All they did was say. So it must be saying that
okay, in one way to explain this is okay, but again, it's
sort of like the מגדף. megadef. It's not about the act of
saying a formula, it's about an expression of a test of a
thought, of an idea, of a claim, and therefore a lot of
it is sort of the idea that's being expressed, not just the
physical action that is happening. I do have to go mention a
there's a רי"ף Rif in Sanhedrin, huge רי"ף, Rif, an entire page.
He quotes a major question about what was the גרסא, girsa, some
say גרסא girsa איע, i'ah, אין, in, ראייה. re'iyah. They say they
ask רב האי גאון Rav Hai Gaon what the גרסא girsa was
and he said this was the גרסא girsa but רב האי גאון
Rav Hai Gaon never explained what it meant. Whole long discussion about
this line, what does it mean הואיל וישנם בראייה. hovei yeshnam bire'iyah.
In the end he says his גרסא girsa is הואיל וישנם באיע,
hovei yeshnam bi'i'ah, and איע i'ah or some say באין, bi'in, and
what that means is אלף יוד אלף, aleph yud aleph, אלף יוד
הא, aleph yud hey, and what he says that means is you
can do עדים זוממים eidim zomemim without an action. How? Because one
עד eid can testify and say the false testimony and they they
turn to the other עד eid as in what do you say?
And he says and he says mhm, mhm, ah, uh-huh. So there
he says that's what איע i'ah means. So he says you're not
moving your lips. Uh-huh, uh-huh, you didn't move your lips. And therefore
since it's possible to do without an action, therefore it's considered אין
בו מעשה. ein bo ma'aseh. All right, anyway, so that was a
fascinating debate of the questions about an action. On the one hand
it started with a question about one לאו, lav. two מיתות. Rabbi
Yochanan said one חטאת, Reish Lakish says two. So therefore that was
the debate about why ידעוני is not mentioned. Is it because of
Rabbi Yochanan's point of one חטאת or is it because what Reish
Lakish then says because there is no action. And then that leads
to the other debate of Rabbi Akiva, when Rabbi Akiva says you're
חייב for מגדף megadef a חטאת, does he say no action, which
is what Rabbi Yochanan says, or does he say there's a minimal
standard of action, and the difference again would be ידעוני. If it's
no action, ידעוני should be an issue. If there is a minimal
standard of action, that's why it's not on there. And then we
get to the question about what is or is not considered an
action according to the חכמים. Chachamim. Reish Lakish says moving lips, bowing
down, flapping arms, that would be an action for Rabbi Akiva, not
for חכמים. Chachamim. Rabbi Yochanan says that bowing down is an action
for everybody, why is moving lips not an action, why is מגדף
megadef different, and leads to interesting questions about when speech is about
the physical act as opposed to when speech is an expression of
some thought or some idea. Let us try with the five minutes
left to at least to get a little bit further, so much
for me thinking we're going to catch up. Oh my god. אוכל
חלב. Ochel cheilev. Now, one who ate forbidden fat. תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabbanan, that's in the list. כל חלב שור וכשב ועז לא תאכלו.
Kol cheilev shor vechesev ve'ez lo socheilu. לחייב על כל אחת ואחת.
Lechayev al kol achas ve'achas. So it says don't eat the fat
of any ox, sheep, or whatever goat. So here again the question
is, do you if you do all
three in one stage of forgetfulness, three חטאת or one חטאת.
So it says to get it says it like that, it lists
the animals differently to tell you a separate חטאת for each one.
דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi Yishmael. That's what Rabbi Yishmael says. וחכמים
אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the Sages say, אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayav
ela achas. No, only one. So נימא בהא קמיפלגי, neima beha kamifligi,
maybe this is the debate. Rabbi Yishmael סבר savar לוקין על לאו
שבכללות. lokin al lav shebechalalus. רבנן סברי אין לוקין על לאו שבכללות.
Rabbanan savri ein lokin al lav shebechalalus. Now that and so although
you would have thought and I said it but incorrectly by the
context that we're talking about a חטאת, the גמרא understands it and
reads it in the context of how many lashes do you get?
If you did in one if you went ahead and did ate
all three after having been warned, okay, would you get one somebody
says don't eat that, that don't eat that fat or that fat,
that's חלב cheilev of a שור, shor, that's חלב cheilev of a
כשב, chesev, that's חלב cheilev of an עז, ez, and you ate
all three. So if it said don't eat that, that, that and
they were all the same חלב cheilev and I ate them all,
it would be one לאו מלקות, lav malkus, I just did one
big act. But if they are three separate things, would that be
three separate מלקויות? malkiyos? That's how the גמרא interprets it, that's a
מלקות malkus question. And it says נימא בהא קמיפלגי, neima beha kamifligi,
maybe this is the debate. Rabbi Yishmael סבר savar לוקין על לאו
שבכללות, lokin al lav shebechalalus, you get מלקות malkus for a generic
לאו. lav ורבנן סברי אין לוקין על לאו שבכללות, Verabbanan savri ein
lokin al lav shebechalalus, you do not. Now normally when this debate
is stated, what it means is what it means is is do
you get מלקות malkus at all? If the Torah says a very
generic לאו, lav. לא תאכלו על הדם, lo socheilu al hadam, what
does that mean? Half a dozen different things. So maybe you don't
get מלקות malkus for any, it's too generic. But here it doesn't
mean that. Here it means if it says don't do A, B,
and C, do you get a separate מלקות malkus for each? No,
the גמרא is interpreting this as a מלכות question, okay, not as
a חטאת question. So the גמרא says לעולם סבר רבי ישמעאל אין
לוקין על לאו שבכללות. Le'olam savar Rabi Yishmael ein lokin al lav
shebechalalus. No, I can tell you רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael would normally
say, normally the rule would be if it said don't do A,
B, or C, it really means one. ושאני הכא דמיסרי ליה קרא,
Veshani hacha demisrei lei kra, the פסוק pasuk is extra. נכתב קרא
כל חלב לא תאכלו, Nichtav kra kol cheilev lo socheilu, just say
don't eat fat. שור כשב ועז למה לי? Shor kesev va'ez lama
li? Why did it have to specifically mention them? שמע מינה לחלק,
Shma mina lachaleik, to tell you that each one is separate. I
know. ורבנן, Verabanan, the רבנן Rabanan would say, אי לאו דכתב שור
וכשב ועז, Ei lav dechasav shor vechesev va'ez, had it not said
that, הוה אמינא אפילו חלב חיה חייב במשמע. Hava amina afilu cheilev
chaya chayav bemashma. It had to say that because it had to
say only these and the חלב Cheilev of a חיה Chaya like
a deer is okay. So it's not saying these
to say each one
is separate, it's saying these to say these and not a deer,
not a חיה. Chaya. להכי כתב שור וכשב ועז, Lehachi kasav shor
vechesev va'ez, that's why it says it. למימרא דחלב שור וכשב ועז
הוא דאסור, Lemeimra decheilev shor vechesev va'ez hu de'asur, only that is
forbidden, אבל דחיה שרי, Aval dechaya shari, by חיה Chaya it's permissible.
So the גמרא says okay, שפיר קאמרי, Shapir ka'amrei, that's an excellent
response. אלא היינו טעמא דרבי ישמעאל, Ela hainu ta'ama deRabi Yishmael, fine,
here's רבי ישמעאל's Rabi Yishmael's reasoning. דקסבר אם כן לכתוב כל חלב
שור לא תאכלו. Dechasvar im kein lichtov kol cheilev shor lo socheilu.
It could have just said ox and by ox I would have
inferred the בהמה Behema and I would have excluded חיה. Chaya. כשב
ועז למה לי? Kesev va'ez lama li? Why did it have to
say also the sheep and the goat? שמע מינה לחלק, Shma mina
lachaleik, to tell me each one is a separate לאו. lav. ורבנן,
Verabanan, the רבנן Rabanan would say, סברי אי כתב רחמנא כל חלב
שור, Savri ei kasav Rachmana kol cheilev shor, if it just said
ox, הוה אמינא נילף שור שור מסיני. Hava amina neilaf shor shor
miSinai. We learn it out from like סיני Sinai and from שבת.
Very sometimes תורה Torah says שור Shor and we learn out that
it really means all animals. מה גבי סיני חיה ועוף כיוצא בהן,
Ma gabi Sinai chaya va'of kiyotzei bahen, the same way by סיני
Sinai where it says, you know, by it says by שבת, למען
ינוח שורך וחמורך. Lema'an yanuach shorecha vachamorecha. Okay, and שור Shor means
all animals. אף גבי אכילה חיה ועוף כיוצא בהן. Af gabi achila
chaya va'of kiyotzei bahen. So therefore if it just sort of said
שור, Shor, I would have not said בהמה, Behema, I would have
said all animals. להכי כתב רחמנא שור וכשב ועז. Lehachi kasav Rachmana
shor vechesev va'ez. למימרא דהני דאסור וחיה ועוף שרי. Lemeimra dehanei de'asur
vechaya va'of shari. So again, it has to say these three to
tell you only these, not חיה, Chaya, not birds. And it could
not have just said שור, Shor, we would have overly generalized. So
the גמרא again says שפיר קאמרי, Shapir ka'amrei, that's a great response.
אלא פיין היינו טעמא, Ela fine hainu ta'ama, דקסבר השתא נכתוב כל
חלב כשב לא תאכלו. dechasvar hashta lichtov kol cheilev kesev lo socheilu.
Don't eat the חלב Cheilev of a sheep. Sheep it doesn't say
by סיני, Sinai, by שבת, and I wouldn't have overly generalized. I
would have just said it meant בהמה. Behema. So the גמרא אי
נמי כל חלב עז לא תאכלו. Ei nami kol cheilev ez lo
socheilu. שור וכשב ועז למה לי? Shor vechesev va'ez lama li? Why
did it have to say all three? שמע מינה לחלק, Shma mina
lachaleik, to tell you each one is separate. ורבנן סברי, Verabanan savri,
the רבנן Rabanan would hold, אי כתב כל חלב כשב, Ei kasav
kol cheilev kesev, if it had just said sheep, הוה אמינא חלב
כשב אסור ושור ועז שרי. Hava amina cheilev kesev asur veshor va'ez
shari. I would have, okay, I wouldn't have overly generalized, I would
have been overly narrow. I would have said fine, only a sheep.
וכי תימא מאי אולמיה דכשב? Vechi teima mai ulmeih dechesev? And I
would have said okay, but why just a sheep? That would have
been arbitrary. I would have had to know it meant it as
a representative. No. Sheep maybe has something special, especially when it comes
to fat. What does sheep have? משום דנתרבה באליה.
Mishum denisraba be'alya.
It has the fat tail, and that's a special thing that's brought
on the מזבח Mizbe'ach only by a sheep. So therefore if the
תורה Torah just said sheep, I would have said it meant only
sheep. Sheep are special when it comes to fat. כדתניא, Kedisanya, like
we taught in the ברייתא, Beraisa, רבי חנניה, Rabi Chananya, למה מנה
הכתוב אימורין בשור ומנה אימורין בכשב ומנה אימורין בעז? Lama mana haksav
imurin beshor u'mana imurin bechesev u'mana imurin be'ez? Why by בכור Bechor
did it say you have to offer up the אימורין Imurin and
it said explicitly שור כשב ועז? Shor kesev va'ez? Why did it
say all three? דכתיב אך בכור שור או בכור כשב או בכור
עז לא תפדה את דמם תזרוק ואת חלבם תקטיר. Dechsiv ach bechor
shor o bechor kesev o bechor ez lo sifdeh es damam tizrok
ve'es chelbam taktir. So why did it mention all three? צריכי, Tzrichi,
it had to tell me I offer up all three. דאי כתב
שור, De'ei kasav shor, had it just said offer the fat of
an ox, הוה אמינא כשב ועז לא ילפינן מיניה. Hava amina kesev
va'ez lo yalfinan mineih. You can't apply it to sheep and goats.
דאיכא למפרך מה לשור שכן נתרבה בנסכים. De'ika limfrach ma leshor shekein
nisraba binesachim. By an ox normally you give more stuff on the
מזבח Mizbe'ach anyway. It has a bigger amount that you give about
the wine and the oil. So maybe because you give more, you
would give the חלב Cheilev for that and not the other stuff.
נכתוב רחמנא בכשב ונילף שור ועז מיניה מכשב. Nichtov Rachmana bechesev veneilaf
shor va'ez mineih mechesev. So just write by a sheep, if you
give the fat of a sheep, you should give the fat of
an ox and a goat. No. איכא למפרך מה לכשב שכן נתרבה
באליה. Ika limfrach ma lechesev shekein nisraba be'alya. That is special, that
has a fat tail. So maybe only sheep you give the fat,
not the other stuff. נכתוב רחמנא עז ונילף שור וכשב מיניה. Nichtov
Rachmana ez veneilaf shor vechesev mineih. Fine, say by a goat and
learn out from that. No. איכא למפרך מה לעז שכן נתרבה אצל
עבודת כוכבים. Ika limfrach ma le'ez shekein nisraba eitzel avodas kochavim. When
it comes to עבודה זרה, the only קרבן korban. you can bring
is from a goat. So therefore each one has something special and
therefore you had to tell me give the fat of each one.
So therefore here too, each one, if you said fat is forbidden,
because the fat is forbidden is connected to also the fat of
a קרבן, korban. you couldn't have said the fat of one is
forbidden, I would have been too narrow, I wouldn't have generalized. So
the גמרא just continues, I know we're going a little over, but
let's try to get to the end of this idea, okay No,
you could make a challenge. מה לכשב ועז, Mah l'kesev ve-ez, the
two of those are special that they're part of, that they're brought
for a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So you can't infer an ox
from it. לא נכתוב כשב ונילף משור ועז, Lo nichtov kesev v'neilaf
mishor ve-ez, don't write sheep and learn from an ox and a
goat. איכא פירכא, Ika pircha, מה לשור ועז שכן ישנן בעבודת כוכבים.
mah l'shor ve-ez sheken yeshnan b'avodat kochavim. An ox and a goat
are different קרבנות korbanot for עבודה זרה and not a sheep, so
maybe that's what's special about them. לא נכתוב עז ונילף משור וכשב,
Lo nichtov ez v'neilaf mishor ve-chesev, don't write goat, learn from an
ox and a sheep. איכא פירכא, Ika pircha, מה, mah, there's something
special. מה לשור וכשב שכן יש בו צד ריבוי. Mah l'shor ve-chesev
sheken yesh bo tzad ribui. Both an ox and a sheep has
something extra on the מזבח. mizbeach. The sheep has the fat tail,
the ox has the largest amount of the wine and the oil.
היכא לא ילפי מהדדי. Heicha lo yalfi me-hadadi. Therefore, it had to
say all three. There is no way you could have learned any
one from the others. שפיר קאמר ליה, Shapir ka'amar lei, that's a
good response. We're back to the point. It had to say all
three. So how do you say that it means separate prohibitions? אלא
לעולם, Ela l'olam, you're right. טעמא דרבי ישמעאל כדאמרינן מעיקרא. Ta'ama d'Rabbi
Yishmael k'de-amrinan me-ikara. If so, go back to what we said first.
נכתוב כל חלב לא תאכלו, Nichtov kol chelev lo tocheilu, just say
fat. מה אמרת, Mah amarta, what was your challenge to that? האי
דכתיב שור וכשב ועז למעוטי חלב חיה. Hai de-chtiv shor ve-chesev ve-ez
l'ma'utei chelev chaya. So you said, no, no, no, it had to
say שור כשב ועז, shor kesev ve-ez, otherwise I would have applied
it even to a חיה, chaya, even to a bird. No, I
wouldn't have done that. האי דכתיב קרא בעניינא דקדשים. Hai de-chtiv kra
b'inyana d'kodashim. It says it by קרבנות. korbanot. What does it say
by חלב? chelev? It says כל חלב שור וכשב ועז לא תאכלו.
Kol chelev shor ve-chesev ve-ez lo tocheilu. It says... what's the פסוק?
pasuk Excuse me. רש"י Rashi says... I'm sorry... and then we'll end
with it. I'll just quote you the פסוק. כי כל אוכל חלב
מן הבהמה אשר תקריבו ממנה קרבן לה'. Ki kol ochel chelev min
ha-behemah asher takrivu mimena korban l'Hashem. It says if you eat the
חלב chelev from a בהמה behemah that you're going to bring a
קרבן. korban, So it didn't have to say שור וכשב ועז. shor
ve-chesev ve-ez. It says from an animal you'll bring a קרבן. korban.
So it didn't have to say שור וכשב ועז. shor ve-chesev ve-ez.
And because it did, that tells me a separate לאו lav for
each one. Okay, but it's not a בהמה אשר תקריבו ממנו. behemah
asher takrivu mimenu. So בעניינא דקדשים. b'inyana d'kodashim. ודבר הלמד מעניינו, V'davar
ha-lamed me-inyano, and you're going to learn it from the context. It
says קרבן, korban you'll learn it from קרבן. And just one more
line. מכלל דרבנן סברי לא ילפינן דבר הלמד מעניינו. Michlal d'rabanan savri
lo yalfinan davar ha-lamed me-inyano. So that's now the answer to the
rabbis. Why did it have to say שור וכשב ועז shor ve-chesev
ve-ez as it says something you bring a קרבן from? We could
have figured that out. So those things are extra. So the גמרא
says לא דכולי עלמא ילפינן דבר הלמד מעניינו והכא בהא קמיפלגי. Lo
d'chulei alma yalfinan davar ha-lamed me-inyano v'hacha b'ha kamiflagi. Here's the debate.
רבי ישמעאל סבר למדין לאו מלאו בין מלאו בין מכרת. Rabbi Yishmael
savar lamedin lav mi-lav bein mi-lav bein mi-karet. Rabbi Yishmael says you
learn it whether from a לאו lav or from כרת. I'll say
what that means in a second. רבנן לאו מלאו ילפינן לאו מכרת
לא ילפינן. Rabanan lav mi-lav yalfinan lav mi-karet lo yalfinan. I know,
it's a mouthful. And the rabbis say, let's say this somehow. The
rabbis say you learn from a לאו, not from כרת. What does
it mean? The פסוק that says מן הבהמה אשר תקריבו ממנה קרבן
לה' min ha-behemah asher takrivu mimena korban l'Hashem is by כרת. כי
כל אוכל חלב מן הבהמה אשר תקריבו ממנה קרבן לה'. Ki kol
ochel chelev min ha-behemah asher takrivu mimena korban l'Hashem. The פסוק כל
חלב שור וכשב ועז לא תאכלו Kol chelev shor ve-chesev ve-ez lo
tocheilu is by the לאו. Can I say since by כרת it's
talking about the animals of קרבנות, korbanot, by the לאו it is
as well? Or do I say no, no, no, what it says
by כרת is what it says by כרת. You can't apply that
to the לאו. So Rabbi Yishmael says since by כרת it's clearly
talking about those animals, it didn't have to repeat it by the
לאו. Since it did repeat it, it's to tell me that each
one is a separate prohibition and you get separate מלקות malkot for
each one.
The rabbis say I could not have
applied כרת to the לאו and therefore by the לאו if it
wanted to tell me just those animals it had to say it
explicitly. I would not have learned it out and therefore it is
only one מלקות. malkot. So in the end we have left this
discussion of חטאת and now we're discussing when the תורה Torah says
all those three things, don't eat the חלב, chelev, do you get
one set of מלקות malkot or three sets of מלקות malkot depending
on whether I could have anyway known that having it learned it
out from כרת.